computer all right so today's topic as
suggested by daniel
is drugs as eric smokes
and i'm off it from monday to friday uh
who would like to start and share and i
don't know where this is going because i
don't even know what the
intention was of discussing drugs i was
hoping there'd be enough of us to split
into
two groups because i was very curious to
see which direction it went in two ways
but whatever direction it goes i am done
with so
anybody want to start
uh well yeah sure i'll just start the
discussion
you know uh as we know it's a little
complex
because there's like kind of
your your medical drugs that you might
be taking
because you have some medical condition
um you know these are super wide ranging
and then you've also got there's a lot
of drugs
that are kind of prescribed for mental
health and
anxiety and antidepressants
then then there's like your illicit
drugs
um which are also wide-ranging i mean it
goes everything from
um beer and and liquor
um all the way up to things that can
kill you
if you take just a little bit just a
tiny bit too much you know heroin
fentanyl
like it runs the gamut um with all these
different effects
um i don't remember
explicitly suggesting this topic but
apparently you do so i'm not sure which
i was referring to when that comment was
made but when i came here i was thinking
more about the
non-prescribed drugs and
part of the problem could be that we
even have a dichotomy between
what's prescribed and and not you know
marijuana
is not prescribed it's becoming
legal yes and it is prescribed in some
cases but it's it's not the go to
um in some places and we've
i've only got my small view of just
where i am in the us and it's probably
so
different in different parts of the
world
and by the way you may have said
something other than drugs i heard drugs
because no i think it was actually me
i think it was actually me that
suggested drugs yeah yeah i was thinking
fair enough
all right well okay maybe daniel said it
too i don't remember yeah actually
it was me be my memory problem instead
of my hearing problems
would you like to share it uh yeah i
mean i think daniel's right to pick up
on the on the
loadedness of the word itself right and
that there it means lots and lots of
different things to lots and lots of
different people i mean uh
technically speaking a drug is anything
which you put in your body which alters
your
physiology right and and that includes
mental states right and so yeah coffee
sugar you know these things these things
technically speaking of drugs as well
and so
they are everywhere right and um
the prescription drugs which are somehow
legitimized in the minds of most people
versus the illegal drugs right which you
can't get on prescription you can only
buy
uh on the black market it's it's it's
it's a somewhat arbitrary division right
i mean
it's it's a historical thing i mean for
many many many years opium was legal and
widely used and they were opium dens
that people went to and then at some
point
it became illegal similarly with
marijuana right it was legal for most of
human history and then
you know reefer madness came along and
everyone went nuts over
over the effects of marijuana so it's
it's it's a really weird line
it's i mean the fact is that there are
drugs everywhere and they do have
effects on our body and some of those
effects are beneficial and when they're
beneficial they cure illness we call
those drugs medicines right but but
there but
the ability to alter our physiology
and or our mental state through the
deliberate
imbibement of these it's a gift from god
right i mean it's an opportunity
to um take control of and accelerate our
development both individually and
collectively and
and but instead of using them for that
we tend to
use them for uh sedation
and um
modification of the concerns of the
broader society right we don't like that
kind of behavior here's a pill that will
that will modify that kind of behavior
and this
cycle that we're in of pharmaceutical
companies
essentially inventing conditions but
don't worry we have a cure for it right
i mean weak
flow syndrome or something you know
restless leg syndrome all these kinds of
nonsensical things
which are just quirks you know what i
mean they're just quirks of it you know
these things don't
anxiety is another great one right
anxiety is
for all of us something that we all go
through right and rather
and and so the the medical profession
sort of labels this as an undesirable
state when you
when you when you experience this state
here take this pill so you don't have to
experience
this unpleasant state but you know that
takes away any opportunity for examining
your anxiety the sources of that anxiety
incorporating that you know
accepting that sometimes you're anxious
right and other times you're not anxious
and every time you get anxious you take
a pill you fuck up
you fuck up your normal internal
chemistry making you more susceptible to
anxiety in the future right and so yeah
i mean i could go on and on and on and
on but drugs
it seems to me that a lot of the illegal
drugs are the drugs that could actually
be of benefit when used correctly and a
lot of legal drugs are actually
killing people poisoning people um and
robbing people of their lives and
and i'll stop there all right my turn
um so as someone who's been diagnosed
with anxiety
and when i got diagnosed with anxiety it
was an
aha moment that this permanent feeling
that i had had in my chest and stomach
had a name to it i think that's very
different that's different by the way i
think going in and out of it right just
like depression is different than being
sad it's like a constantness that being
said i went on a drug last year because
i felt i was taking out my anxiety on my
kid
and it made it but i was going off of
pot at the same time because you weren't
allowed to take them at the same time
and so i was very anxious in the
beginning and that could be a sign
you're taking the wrong one i took it
for a few months and then tapered off
myself
and i think it was the wrong one but it
really helped with my anxiety in the
opposite way it was supposed to because
of what you were talking about right
that it kind of amped it up and then
when i went off of it
i was like okay this is this is a little
better that being said
anxiety is my constant companion and i
need to work with it
uh but i do think those kind of drugs
the mental drugs
on a case-by-case individual basis you
use them to get through a hard time and
they're life-saving
but the fact that so many people in our
population are on it
if that's a societal issue right if like
five percent of people are depressed and
anxious
okay i can see why you'd want a drug for
that but
when 30 40 50 of people
are that maybe it's society that needs
to figure out how to not
be a depressive anxious fuck show right
like
what the hell is going on um i have
taken
illicit drugs in my life and they have
been
um part of my spiritual awakening
whether seeking them out for that or not
right when i've done mushrooms as a
teenager it wasn't to have a spiritual
experience
when i smoked pot it i admit it's both
my
um prescription and it's my addiction
and being conscious
in that every time i go through an
addictive cycle i get more aware of it
and so right now
i'm smoking it only on the weekends and
i'm only on week two or three of that
but this seems to work for me like okay
this seems to be something i can put it
off to the weekend as opposed to going
off it for a month and then going back
on it
and it's in my system long enough that i
don't go through the withdrawal and yet
i'm clear minded during the week it's
it's it's good for me
i also live in a city where we have i
mean there's a big opioid crisis in the
states just even more so here we have
more of a heroin fentanyl issue
and it's in our lower east end we have
the insight and safe injection place
but with covid19 and this coming
together and one of my friends just
posted like there's you know maybe a few
hundred people who died from covet and
there's been that many people dying from
overdoses in one month and no one seems
to care and i'm like i don't think it's
that we don't care i can tell you i used
to check on people who were sleeping
to make sure on the street to make sure
they were breathing right like
look and make sure now i'm like i don't
know i you could have covet right i'm
gonna risk my life and my dad's life
like it's like oh and there's it's so
hard because there's these people who
if they had connection it makes
addiction a lot less if you have
community if you feel like your
work your society supports you then
there's ways to come back from it but in
a society that's just like you're wrong
you're wrong on
it and like your life truly doesn't
matter
right and yet we're all paying the price
for that in vancouver
they're on the bus system they don't
know how to put a mask on they don't
know how to wash their like
they know how to wash their hands but
they not in the right state of mind to
be able to do that
and so they're spreading it amongst
themselves and they're spreading
the rest of the population and it just
show like we are connected we don't look
out for everyone if we don't have ways
of giving people purpose and loving them
where they
are then i don't know then we're all i
don't know how else to say it like we're
all paying the price for that and
especially the people who have these
addictions and are losing loved ones
with fentanyl i mean so many people i
don't remember what the drug is the
counteracts fentanyl
but a ton of people are walking around
with those needles
because you can encounter somebody at
any time
that is has gone through a an overdose
and it's it's life-changing
well if savings right um so that's
yeah it's all of it right it's the
prescription stuff and then it's
for-profit prescription
so it's like i go to my doctor and they
get they get somewhat of a cut of the
pharmaceuticals it's all they know
they're basically just a really
educated drug dealer it's like oh we
there's a drug for that and i'm
anti-drug from my doctors and so i look
like i'm
i'm like yeah i smoke pot but i don't
want to take your anxiety pill i don't
want to take something for pain it
doesn't work
so why would i take it when my body just
has to deal with that on top of
everything else
and um it feels like
like i'm not allowed to choose what goes
in my body right there's drugs i want to
be allowed to take i'm not allowed to
take
and drugs they want me to take that i
don't want to take and i'm the one who
experiences the mind altercation and the
body altercation
right so i should be the one to decide
so that is
my vent on current state of drugs of all
of the areas uh we can
we can have a bit of an open discussion
on this and then move on to
our beautiful future for drugs
i i like what you said about how the the
incentive structures
are off um the incentive to prescribe
drugs from the medical side and the
pharmaceutical side
uh from my perspective the incentives
are off
from your uh illicit drug
side uh your bartender
has an incentive generally to
give you more beer um if they're good
bartender
you know they'll make sure you have a
ride home or
they'll cut you off before something bad
happens
but that's rare um
your pot dealer doesn't really have much
i mean i've seen people people who
their lives are not going well
and their pot dealer continues to say
you know you
you just need a different strain of pot
i think
or just you need more or have you tried
this dab
thing or switch to edibles they're they
they're your best friend but to think
that they don't have an incentive
if they don't have an incentive to say
maybe you should take a break for a
while
see what that does um so our incentives
are off all around um
what comes to mind for me on all of this
is
that study that i pulled up over here
it's
by someone it says bk alexander
done in the 1980s
this was is referred to as rat park
and they gave the rats access to
morphine and which
would yeah make you feel amazing and
they had
uh basically rats in rat utopia
um rat connections socializing
all the toys and whatever rat utopia and
they
it was like they didn't even touch the
morphine and then they put rats
more isolated in in bad situations and
they drank themselves
to death on the morphine i think that's
what we're experiencing we have a
society
that doesn't make sense anymore um
from our evolutionary roots um
another good example of this is the uh
the adhd medication that's prescribed
all around and i do think some people
help some people
but on balance i think it says more
about
the society that we're asking people
to live in that we need to give them
these drugs
then they don't there's got to be we
need a more
rat utopia a human utopia where
we're living in our bodies if we had
playscapes on every corner
or something and you could go do the
monkey bars you would be happier you
wouldn't need to check out
with these really powerful drugs um
i think i also have adhd and i don't i
take medication every once in a while
for it
it does really help to make my thought
process
linear and be able to communicate better
that being said
i don't want my thought process let me
urine to be able to communicate it like
it's doing amazing things without that
when i let it go
into its neurodiverse state that's what
the world needs and yet yeah society's
not set up for that at all
um one of the other things i want to
bring up from like high school
is we had this dare program right i
think a lot of people went through
something similar
that villainizes drugs not alcohol
because that was somewhat legal just
wait till you're 18 but like marijuana
oh no like heaven forbid
um and then you partake in marijuana
and realize oh this is actually like way
safer than pot on i'm sorry than alcohol
on like
every level even if you're gonna drive
on it which
don't do that but like the difference
between driving on a couple beers and
driving on you know part of a joint
is very different you don't get violent
you don't get but it's that like then
it's like oh wait what other drugs are
they keeping from me
right like like if this one is this this
beneficial what about heroin i'd have
never tried heroin
like what about these other ones and you
end up getting it's like it's a gateway
drug i think because of that
not because it's actually a gateway drug
it's like if you try anything other than
marijuana marijuana is
somewhat safer although we've like
concentrated it more and more but
it's that villainization from like
reefer madness time
that brings it's like okay well if you
were wrong on this
yeah why aren't you wrong on all of them
instead of saying here's alcohol here's
what it does
here's pot here's what it does here's
mdma this is what this is like
you know here's ketamine this is what
this is like
you know and actually giving you
information
they they're you know
exactly what you described as what's
happening
and the thing things like things it's
very things like anxiety and adhd i mean
i think you're absolutely right then the
adhd
is the the medication does help some
people no question about it similarly
with anxiety medication it is helpful
for some people
if the cause of their dysfunction
is a chemical imbalance in the brain
chemistry somehow right and then
adding a chemical to that brain you can
put that in balance right and
and offer some relief right but i i
would contend that
kind of as you both said right that an
awful lot of anxiety and an awful lot of
what manifests as adhd is simply people
not in a world that makes sense to them
i mean adhd
for me i mean as a having having been a
teacher for 15 years
a lot of adhd diagnoses is simply unruly
children now who don't want to submit to
the stupid routines and the stupid shit
they have to do at school
and they play out it for in whatever
reason as a as a form of rebellion and
they're labeled as hca
given ritalin to sedate them you know
what i mean this happens a lot
this happens a lot and i i didn't mean
to imply before jubilee that
there is no place for medication in
these kinds of issues i don't mean to
imply that at all but
you know to assume that
the problem lies in the physiology of
the child and that it can be put right
with a pill
rather than asking the question hang on
a minute is there something in the
environment at large that is causing
these huge spikes in anxiety and
depression and adhd
and diabetes and you know i mean all of
this stuff and so the use of drugs to
cure symptoms is is is is is is an
abomination right i mean drugs if they
are going to be used should be used to
enhance
health right this is this is this this
is this is the great opportunity that
understanding that adding certain
substances to your body
can create certain effects right well
now you can actually use that not not
not wait until you're at death's door
and then give you something to relieve
the pain right but
but you know have a menu of i guess when
leading into the beautiful future right
but you know have a menu of things
available kind of what you're saying
this is the thing this is what it does
and in a
enlightened society you can choose the
things which are going to advance the
kinds of
qualities that you want to pursue the
things that you want to do with your
life right
um so yeah it's it's it's it's
all upside down it's all upside down the
drugs which can when used properly
advance you in your life and i mean even
things like alcohol right used properly
alcohol you know you have a couple of
drinks in the evening you can have a
real laugh with people in a way that you
don't when you haven't had a couple of
drinks right and i'm not talking about
getting violent and kicking in shot
windows and all of that kind of thing
but a future you know
alcohol can really grease the wheels of
social contact you know certainly for
some people certainly for me i find
three or four beers
and i'm much more gregarious and
and you know naturally easy to you know
find myself naturally easy and
comfortable around people so you know
all of these things used properly have
their place
but yeah the default mode is
it's curing sickness and it's um
alleviating symptoms right that's that's
what it's about is to alleviate symptoms
and that that seems
a really wasteful use of the potential
of drugs
do you want to show your beautiful
future daniel
oh gosh i wasn't ready for that i just
wanted to make sure that eric had said
everything he he really wanted to i was
like here's the moment what else
haven't you said that you you know you
want to say
that's what i was thinking thanks thank
you for listening thank you for giving
me the space
um well i'll
i'll tell you what what comes to mind is
i am very concerned about addiction
um i think that you know what was said
about having a
understanding about what different drugs
do
for you the danger of addiction is still
there and i think the addiction
is still related to our society
our world that doesn't serve us well
like the rat park
example um i think that if you're
in the bad uh example of the rat park
you're in the crappy
world even if you understood you've got
these different substances here's what
they do
your if your connections to other people
your social life your physical life
you're not exercising etc the
cards can be really stacked against you
so when you do use one of these
substances
and it makes you feel so good in a way
you weren't feeling
that's when the addiction i think takes
hold
um so i think part of this
is is doing what you can to
develop a life that
is good that you're exercising
that you're you're maintaining social
structures
uh and that will keep the the tendency
to become
addicted to something um
at bay uh that's oh
i guess the the last the other thing
that comes to mind is
i do really think
i think people who
are suggesting to use
um especially illicit drugs um
like including marijuana um
i think that they have a bit of a
responsibility
to talk about how it works for them
um i think
that you know and usually the ages when
when people start to try these things
um if if you're suggesting that
i try ketamine because it'll make me
feel good
i want to know a lot about what your
life is like
that will give me a better sense of
some other things about whether you do
this especially if you
if you take this substance on a regular
basis um
but just to say hey try it once because
it'll be fun for this one
day um but i don't know anything
else about what the rest of your life is
like
i think there's a responsibility there
to say
you know my life is pretty much together
or my life is really
crappy actually and i'm hanging on to
these substances
because i don't have much else the
proper access to pharmacology though
right you could take a lot of the risk
away because if you you could you could
take the ketamine and then if you don't
like it you could take the antidote and
five minutes later it's gone it's the
effects gone right and and it's over so
you there is no reason in the world why
things like that can't be tried with a
safety net like that
pretty much all drugs have an antidote
to them
interesting what's the antidote to pot
yeah i was just using that as a general
example
but my pot dealer's incentives to
keep me on it um might not be lined up
with
my understanding of whether absolutely
you know had done any work to understand
whether he's addicted or not
absolutely so i'm going to share my
beautiful feature and then we can switch
over into the
adjacent possible part um i
come down on the side of libertarian on
this one i think all drugs should be
legal
especially the ones that nature grows
the mushrooms the ayahuasca that being
said especially like ayahuasca
you have to do it with somebody who is a
shaman like you can't
it's not something you just
recreationally do with your friends
there is a
health and spiritual outcome that can be
very negative if those things happen
but giving people access to that
information including the pharmaceutical
ones to know
what they do in your body what the
chemical component is and have people be
able to
offer that both but they've been taking
it and not
so you can see more of the incentive
structure see who creates it and why
um and how it makes you feel what the
long-term implications are how many
people get addicted when they take it
have the actual facts instead of
the dare scare tactics having a world
where people can
use these drugs in a safe space and a
society that isn't prone to addiction
because we have rat utopia right we have
human utopia
we have a space of you know you have
connection with community and if it does
if what you have isn't working there's
easy ways to get
friends and connection and there's ways
to if
whatever exercise you want to do it's
available to you whatever diet you need
that's going to
help you is is that being said we're not
just going to get rid of addiction
and so having the ability for people
who are currently using to use in a safe
space
like injection sites but even more than
that like actual villages that are like
hey
we're gonna look after we're gonna make
sure here's where the meals are go to
the meals
here's like where we put the needles
here's how we make this safe until
they're ready
to see their their worth until they're
ready to
to enter an addiction recovery program
and make sure that those are available
as well
and share their stories with each other
right to be able to to empower people to
make to have the
autonomy over their own lives even when
they have an addiction because that's
is a lack of autonomy right it's like
it's substance in charge of you
somewhat instead of another person to be
able to
um have different options
for addiction recovery that the only
option
seems to be a a right like that or n a
that it's like a hundred percent no is
what you have to do because you're
addicted
and that doesn't work for a lot of
people and because it's the only thing
out there then if they are using still
it's like if you go from using a lot to
using less
that is good if you're trying to use
less
and so having the ability to have
different resources right to be able to
know that i could join
a pot support group of people who are
trying to reduce their
usage right as opposed to no you have to
like i'm
five days sober i'm like i'm two days
sober because like and then i'm gonna do
it on friday and then i'll go on monday
i'll be one day sober like this is my
plan
and so to be able to have personal
autonomy
that doesn't have to go through my
doctor necessarily to be able to see the
long-term implications and be able to
see those statistics as well of like how
many people are on
anti-anxiety meds some people are on
opioids why are we
prescribing all of these things why is
that happening like see the
population statistics as well as the
individual ones
in a way of course that is safe for
everyone so that's
i guess a bit of my beautiful future i
would like to see
so it's like basically
it's like the pharmaceutical drugs
whether they're needed or not right
whether
the illicit ones that are addictive and
people are addicted to them and they
illicit ones that are and the
pharmaceutical ones that are beneficial
to people and they want to be able to
have them
i don't know if we want to tackle all
three of those things but i'm sure
there'll be things that touch on
multiple of them in the adjacent
possible what could we do
with 10 000 people and 100 000 you would
want to have access to
for me one of the things that is a
database a database of
pharmaceutical drugs and
non-pharmaceutical drugs but let's start
with the non-pharmaceutical ones
and that like here's how it's derived
here's the safe usage here's its history
and
here's what withdrawal looks like right
like whatever the basics are
in a trustworthy way that isn't the dare
that isn't that like scare tactic but is
truth right
like the other side of pot is people are
like oh it's not addictive
you don't go through withdrawal i'm like
i went through withdrawal several times
with pot actually
and it is it's not addictive in the same
way i'm not going to sell my
you know sell my house that would be
really bad i don't own the house
so i'm not gonna not pay rent to pursue
that addiction
but it doesn't mean it's not an
addiction and just to blanket it is
something that is
more benign than it is is not serving
anyone
so it's like actually and you probably
shouldn't smoke it till you're 25 or so
because your brain's still developing
then
should you really be having alcohol i
don't know should you be doing anything
until you're 25 that seems
i know i did most of mine before i was
25 so
what else what else could we do with 10
000. well so
it's all right so the database thing
it's a tough question because the
problem is so big
it reminds me of the climate change one
like what in the world
could actually be done um
with that many people and that much
money
i'd almost have to think like something
local
um you could do something in one
community
um but if you were to go really big
you could also have some kind of uh
if you're using the internet you could
have some kind of network
for people to tell their stories
i didn't really talk about i barely
touched on this and
and what you're doing jubilee with
telling well this is what
i have done and this is how it affected
me
um we have lost
our well maybe we never had it it's hard
to talk about these things
i don't know how it affects um my career
or
my other social circles this is why
things like aaa
do work because many people go and you
wouldn't know that they
they go um it may be
loosening up a little bit over time but
as long as people can't talk about yeah
you know to have stories where they said
yeah i tried mdma a few times and this
is what was good about it this is what
was bad about it um
i i think that would be very helpful
um i think the dangers
and we can't when we can't talk about it
if people can't talk about these things
even to
their parents um or their friends
and either they're just gonna judge them
immediately or
um i don't know
yeah so with that amount of money and
that many people
you could do a database of of stories
you could do a podcast kind of
thing um you could filter it by
uh the topic by the specific substance
this could
cover pharmaceuticals uh etc
natural plants whatever
um
[Music]
and you know the question that comes to
mind with
doing does this already exist i don't
know i think there are is a website
called
arrowed.com that has a bunch of stories
but
um i don't i don't know what it covers
if it covers pharmaceuticals
etc because like yeah me i i was on
uh i took antidepressants for a while
um and i took after that i took some
anti-anxiety
pills these were all prescribed they
were prescribed
in conjunction with uh
with therapy i think it would be very
dangerous to give somebody those types
of drugs
and just say this is your answer uh
you should be taking because they're not
supposed to be long-term you should be
taking those
with a therapist probably that's a cost
barrier some people are like
i need the drugs i can't afford a
therapist
is also right to to say like i
i went to i was seeing one of my doctors
and they could definitely tell i was
anxious
because that's obvious uh less so now
than it was then
and so they put me in touch with a free
counselor through
canadian you know medical system bc
medical system
and so it was free and i went in he was
like yes i need to see you twice a week
and i was like all right i went to
um schedule my next appointment she's
like i have time three months from now
it's like well he says to see me every
every like
twice a week so if i schedule three
months from now can we do like twice a
week
no no you have to schedule it so i'm
like well what good is every three
months gonna do
like stir up all the shit and then just
like have to deal with it on my own and
yet our entire system is like you need a
doctor like you need a professional and
like actually
other people who are dealing with
anxiety might be
maybe not as helpful as a doctor but
still helpful
yes there's legal ramifications and
everything else but that is one thing
that could happen with 10 000 people
these support groups right is like we
get that there's no
professional here but we're sharing
stories we're showing up once a week and
and saying hey how is your anxiety or
how is your pot addiction or whatever
it is to be able to find 10 000 people
with that same thing right pot
anxiety whatever it happens to be and
like break off into groups
and know you're meeting with the same
people every week and if you don't like
them or they don't like you
right you can find a new group of people
i think it's comforting
you need to break off into groups right
i mean i think there's actually a lot of
potential in this idea i really like
what you said before jubilee about
you know like aa and n a are about
complete abstinence right you get
rewarded for how long your absence is
but but what about an equivalent
anonymous group where
you could go to manage your
whatever it is that you like to take
right and you don't want it to get out
of control
you know you want to keep taking it
because you like it and you feel it does
whatever for you
but you've you know you know you're
susceptible to running out of control
and so a group
that allows you to have those
conversations and share your experiences
you know you have a bad trip right and
there's this group of people that you
can go to you can talk about your
bedroom you may
maybe find some solace in that and so
yeah i really i really like this notion
of support group but i think i actually
think that separating people who
have you know like flirting with
addiction from people that suffer from
anxieties maybe a mistake because i
actually think that their experiences
are
you know there's a lot in common
probably far more in common in their
experience
of their because it's it's it's about
the isolation that your condition brings
to you right i mean i think that's the
fundamental thing and so
i think there's a lot to be shared
across difficulty shall we say do you
see what i mean so yeah yeah yeah
and and this you know we're all about
community building right and it is it is
an opportunity to start building
relationships and community based on
vulnerability and honesty you know what
i mean it's a good thing
it's a good thing yeah and i think one
of the other i don't remember exactly
what the process is i could look it up
again but
it was something along the lines of like
before you use
saying like how you're feeling right and
why you want to do it and then do it
and then say how you feel after right
like i know there's tons of times i
smoke pot especially when i'm in more of
an addictive
phase where i'm like why did i do that i
feel gross like i don't like this
feeling
but it's just a habit so it's like oh
yeah smoke the thing
oh yeah do this but if you're aware of
that process and you're aware of how
often you do it right that's the other
thing when you smoke pot i was like
oh i could use more and it's like
actually it's only been half an hour
right like you don't necessarily know
and to be able to track those things for
yourself
could also be something that we could do
with ten thousand people and a hundred
thousand dollars is
your own tracker and then if that's a
way to get people in so that it's
something that they're feeling empowered
with because they might not
feel comfortable talking other people
about it it could also be like hey do
you want to meet with this group of
people
right whether it's interconnected or not
the ability to talk about these things
without judgment i think
just goes full circle whether you have a
problem you think you have a problem
whether you think you want to try
something and you want to talk about it
before
you you try it instead of just being in
a vacuum
and being able to talk about it
if you are using something i
oh well yeah what i was thinking about
was
one of the aspects of addiction creeps
in
when you're hiding something it becomes
a secret
i mean this is with malt this was
with his uh what's the thing klepto's
people that steal stuff they develop
this secret
pornography they've people develop the
secret
and the same thing with substances uh
feeling like you can't talk about it now
it's your secret thing
that that could really help
um so whatever we're talking about as
far as
non-judgmental uh creating a culture
where and where you're even welcome
if you aren't using any substances just
to be there
and learn um could also be helpful
yeah i mean i think that's one of the
things that aaa like any so
any group it becomes such a religion
like there's
i've wanted to sometimes go right i'm
like i don't have an alcohol problem but
like there's a community there there's
like something there where you can just
go and tell your story
to have that in other pockets so that
you don't need to be 100 off of it right
you can
when you're drunk in the moment you're
high in the moment be like i don't feel
good about this like i want
to get off you know like you're not
allowed to go to a when you're drunk
like that's not understandably um
well i've been going to aaa and
if you show up and you've had a bad day
and you are drunk they're not going to
kick you out
that's good to know they want you to
hear what's going on it is
true there is a slight
uh i don't have a better word for this
there's a slight
cultish aspect in the all or nothing
thing my view on
recovery is
many people need total abstinence
many people if you can if you've had a
problem and you can get sober
then i don't think you should flirt
with going back to trying to drink again
i think that's the answer for most
people but it shouldn't be a dogma
um because there are some people who
did develop an alcohol problem but they
didn't
like lose their house they didn't lose
their job
maybe it just got bad enough and then
they got a dui once and they're like
you know what i need to take a break for
a while
they i think recovery
is getting back to a normal
type of life um where it's
like something like alcohol let's just
say is no longer a problem
for you that could mean you never do it
again or that means
you drink like someone who's not an
addict
uh the someone who gets back
into recovery to drink like someone
who's not an addict
they would be the type of person that's
not really
welcome around aaa anymore even though
they got their life together
because it's abstinence or nothing yeah
yeah that makes sense
but yeah if you were drinking and you
were like oh my god my life is falling
apart
you could i'm not gonna say you can't
beat that
i think the secrecy thing is huge i know
for me
i keep getting messages from the
universe that's like you get to save the
world if you go off of pot and it's not
actually that i'm supposed to go
off of it it's very tied to either be
honest about where you're at don't hide
it
or go off of it those are your two
options and it's really hard for me to
go off of it permanently
and so it's like oh the other option
okay the other option is to share in
that story to just honor that like
our world's a chaotic place right now
and sometimes i do need something to
numb it out sometimes i do need that
but when it's like oh but then people
like then it's
it's vulnerable to share those things
right to be able to have a space to be a
prescription right
you get prescriptions for your for your
weed right yeah
i mean yeah i let it all out trying to
pay full price i'm just curious to ask
you to what degree
do you continue to smoke it because it
has some perceived therapeutic value and
how much is just because you like
smoking it
what what where's the where's the
balance there i don't know when i go off
of it for too long
all of my symptoms get worse so if i go
off of it for two weeks or longer
i have more trouble sleeping in my i
have zero appetite and
i so there's if you're gonna see someone
were to smoke it say once a week
only forever if you just smoked about it
would have its full therapeutic value
for you then if you
did that right okay okay because it
stays in it seems to be like that's
where i'm like okay i don't want to joke
they say 30 days
they say it's in you for 30 days after
you smoked i mean i don't know how true
that is but they do say
and i'm not going through withdrawal
which is the other like if i go off of
it off of it
on day two i'm on in withdrawal which is
weird because i'm always like i'm on day
two
right it's like no i'm not getting the
night sweats or
the overly bitchiness or i'm like okay i
think it's partly because it is the
consciousness right it's like well
i know i can do it again on friday right
so it's like it's not about not having
it
and that's kind of part of it is like
that
but the secrecy having a space where you
can go
and talk about what it's actually like
right ask those questions of yourself
right how much is this helping me
because i've fully admitted i'm like
does it help with pain yes it numbs it a
little bit
but it's basically just it's better to
be high in pain than sober in pain
like you know what i mean it's not like
it's cancelling out the pain completely
it's like yeah i'd rather be a little
stoned than be
have pain all over my body i think
that's a balance
it's like it's not you know people who
don't experience chronic pain can't
really talk about that like it's like
okay like i get why they wouldn't make
that decision but i'm like no there's
and i can see how this addiction cycle
is getting better and better if it was
getting worse and worse
then i would probably seek abstinence
but because it's getting better and
better i'm like
did i tap into something here that's
like about like conscious
addiction i don't know i don't know but
what do we think is the most powerful
thing we could do
like we're not really happy never mind
we don't need to answer that question
yet we can wait a little bit
uh well i'll say that um you know
i've tried a little bit of everything
and a lot of
some things and
i would say i love what was said before
this not political but um
i think jubilee said i'm a libertarian
so i think that has something to do with
freedom
and what i found my
as as i became more aware of
what i was doing my radar became whether
or not
i had freedom so that's what i care
about
do i have the freedom to go where i want
to
do the things that i want to um
take a substance as i want to
or is it controlling me if it's the
other way around
um well if i don't have freedom then i
know it's a problem
for example um if
let's say i want to i can't fly
with uh on an airplane with marijuana on
me
but if my addiction
is keeping me from traveling then i know
that's when it's crossed the line it's
in it's encroaching on my freedom
because i'm like
well i could go you know
i could fly internationally but if i
can't take my pot with me
then maybe i just shouldn't go like at
that point i have to say
this is controlling me i'm not no longer
controlling it
um what if your addiction compels you to
take the risk of
bringing marijuana across the borders
anyway because you can't bear the
thought and i would say it's still a
problem because
i've also done that and i knew
this is very this is very dangerous and
this could be like a federal
crime or something this could be very
bad
but i was willing to take too hot a risk
and it was probably too high of a risk
you gotta say i got to bring marijuana
with me to alberta when i went
pre-covered because it's a prescription
right so it was like yeah fully like my
carry-on with my vaporizers like perfect
for good
that being said there's other right like
that is your level
of knowing whether it's controlling your
life which i think is very powerful
there's people whose
children take marijuana because they
have a seizure thing right and they
can't bring it on a plane it's like
they're not addicted to it it's
literally keeping them
alive yeah of course they're not going
to go on a plane if they can't there's
there's
a reverse uh example of that too
i hurt my back i'm an adult i understand
how um pain relievers work and i
i called someone that i knew had
some powerful pain relievers that would
help me
and they could get them to me right away
so that was actually probably also
illegal
for them to give me their prescription
so i could take them for two days
my back was very bad a lot of pain
that made way more sense the amount of
money and the amount of time it would
have taken to
fully go through all the loopholes to
get the prescription
when my friend just had a couple pills
he could give me
that worked way better but that was also
illegal
yeah i don't hold legality as my moral
compass
but other people do right it's like well
you can't do it it's illegal
and that's kind of the irony like canada
it's not legal right anyone and everyone
can smell pot
i don't know if everyone's allowed to
bring it on a plane i think you are
actually i think it's like tobacco
you're not allowed to bring it to the
states but you can bring it
in uh domestically
um but to know
right and that was one of the reasons i
got a prescription was when i became a
parent i was like oh if they wanted to
they could take my kid away because i
smoke pot i need to have this legality
in place
so that that's not that's not the level
of like hey
because there have been people who've
had their kids taken away because they
smoked pot
which is i think a greater violence than
smoking pot
like having you know being being taken
away from your parents for that reason
but making sure that those
just because something's illegal doesn't
make it immoral but it does put you at a
greater risk
and that's part of the whole sense
making
problem that comes up in game b all the
time does
the way we're doing things even make
sense um
the whole topic of drugs and
pharmaceuticals
no and it's a blatant no in
many different ways
absolutely and that's something that i'm
sure we cannot do with 10 000 people 100
we could but it wouldn't be legal is um
like i have prescriptions here
right that i'm not finishing someone
else has a prescription for them they're
already paid
i love it a drug exchange but you have
to prove you have a prescription
but it's like hey this is free right
here you go
it's not legal in any way so it's not
something but it could be something we
do
five ten years from now when we have i
wonder if i wonder if that could be done
in a legal way though if it was uh done
under medical supervision of some kind
whether that could be done legally
but it's possible it's actually a really
really good idea because there's lots of
people they take painkillers for three
or four days
their pain goes away they've still got a
couple of days worth left you know
and and they just sit in the cupboard
and kids could take them and whatever
right so
i think a lot of people might actually
be glad to get this shit out of the
house
uh so yeah it's it's a really good idea
if you could find a way of doing it
legally that's actually a really good
idea
a drug exchange we just won solution
raising
[Laughter]
better yet we sell them and fund all of
game b
i mean you could you could lobby for
that there's there's
there's like i s like was i think eric
said the
sounds like a legitimate thing that
could
exist um in a legit way like
that's cool and you could more easily
see right if it was something where you
had your
id but it was safe in there you would
see who was like wait you're just
seeking opioids this is
that's not that's that's clear versus
okay no actually you're at the end of
your you know you have that two days of
pain
you have that you're at the end of your
your prescription and you need another
day's worth do you get to do that
because they have four days worth of
pain
but 30 days worth of pills and they're
no longer in pain
and they're like keep taking them it's
in that's a problem right if they could
give them away
they could i mean i guess they could
throw them away but
you can take them to pharmacy i mean at
least here you can they will recycle
them they just
give them out to someone else and they
you know what i mean they already were
made so it feels wasteful to do that
especially when they're already paid for
and already made
but yeah all right now we're getting
down to the last five minutes so what do
you think is the most powerful thing we
could do
um that you would like to see in your
own life or in your community
for 10 with 10 000 people and 100 000
i like the idea of of drugs anonymous
right where it's not about necessarily
quitting and abstaining but you know
just just a place where you can go
and find out you know i like daniel's
edition of um
you know people that just want to try
stuff out and go and talk to people we
ever tried this what's it like
what should i watch out for blah blah
blah blah you know and just just
honest no judgement people talking from
personal experience
and yeah i i think that's yeah i think
there's actually nothing stopping any
group of people start getting that off
the ground right now i mean you don't
need 10
000 people you don't need any money you
know what i mean it's just a question of
someone getting off their arse and
organizing themselves that anyone could
do that at any time
you know yeah in their living room
in your living room you know yeah yeah
absolutely agreed some of these ideas
are absolutely that
you don't actually need ten thousand and
a hundred thousand dollars
about you danielle what do you think is
the most powerful yeah same thing i
would
back off from calling it drugs anonymous
it might be confusing to people
but the idea was talked about um
i i don't know how it relates to that to
a hundred thousand dollars but
a culture where you can
safely talk about this stuff
um pharmaceuticals
well i just want to say including
pharmaceuticals
a lot of people have taken
anti-depressants
and don't know how to say this was good
or this was bad
a culture where we can talk about these
things in in non-judgment
is badly needed uh
so that's yeah that's what i think just
because you guys didn't mention i think
those are both very powerful ideas
but having a not symptom trackers
throwing word what i would talked about
right that like
uh saying what your mood is before you
take it saying just when you take it so
you have that
that um record for yourself
and with the community involvement of
like hey by the way there's four other
people in your area
that are also using would you like would
you all like to meet up would you all
like to have a conversation
and offering that that as well is
something that i think would get people
to use it because it's not if it
especially was a free app
and then also creates that community
around it and
takes away that secrecy component to it
even if you're not comfortable sharing
with your family and friends
where your addictions at that you can
share with strangers
and yourself because yourself is the
most important person to share it with
and it's hard to be honest right it's
hard to know how many times a day or you
take it how much are you taking
what is it making you feel like is this
actually having the outcome you want it
to have
can i add something yeah it seems
this is so interesting to me right now
because
what is what's been said about
some kind of group where you can talk
about this or even
uh an inventory or a journal of this is
what i've been doing this how it's been
making me feel through the week
it's so interesting to me because in
abstinence-only groups
you can still talk about whatever you
have done
or what you're doing but the answer from
the group
is always you have to stop
that's the only response um
and you know i just notice
the difference between what we're
talking about now and what that
environment is like there's only one
response
is abstinence versus uh let's continue
the conversation
right i'm realizing with this thing on
this
current special interest in mlms and
their cult like status
that what people do get out of alcohol
and drug and um
narcotics anonymous is that because
there's a community around abstinence
they know that if they they use that
kind of you know i mean it goes from
like
10 years sober now i'm down to my one
day chip that hurts or i have to if i'm
going to be in use then i
lose this community completely and and
that
for better for worse can keep people
sober
right it's like they want to stay part
of it's like i would rather have the
other side but like i get that for some
people
nothing's perfect it can help keep
people sober is the community
the cult aspect to it um it could be for
better
so it's really tricky
absolutely any closing thoughts eric
before we stop the recording
all right thanks for hanging out we
don't know yet what we're doing next
week but
we'll talk about that off camera